（バロン）「愚者のパズル」に…。
A Fools' Puzzle...
（カイト）ここは…。
（扉の閉まる音）
This is...
ん？！　ドアが！　あっ。
The door!
「塔を上りし者に
福音の鐘は鳴る」。
Those who climb the tower shall hear the bells of gospel chime.
炎…。
Flames?
リフトに乗れってか？
So I'm supposed to get in the lift?
ルークの駒！　ん？！
Rook's piece!
心の声
やっぱり　こいつは　賢者のパズル。
This is definitely a Sage Puzzle.
心の声
このリフトを使って　フロアを移動し
最上階を目指す立体迷路だ。
A three-dimensional maze where I should aim for the highest level using the lift.
マジかよ？！
You're kidding me...
あっ。　ルーク！
Rook!
そういうことか！　ルークを餌にして
俺を「賢者のパズル」に…。
I see...
They used Rook as bait to lure me into a Sage Puzzle!
待ってろ。　ルーク…。
Wait for me, Rook.
今　助ける！
I'm coming for you!
kimi no nounai he shinnyuu nemutteiru sukima ni
I infiltrate your brain while you're sleeping.
Baby, open the gate!
fukuzatsu sugi sekyuriti kakusareru to abakitaku naru
The security's too tough, but I want to expose what's hidden.
barabara ni chirabatteiru pasuwado wo hiroi atsume
I gather the pieces of the shattered password.
kakushin ni sematte iku sono shoutai wo misete
I get close to the core. Show me who you really are!
kantan ni kuria dekinai saki nante motto yomenai
I can't clear it easily. I can't even see what lies ahead.
kaidoku fukanou sumairu kikenna pazuru
Your indecipherable smile is a hazardous puzzle.
rokku sareta doa aru nara zutto tataite miru beki kazana hiraku wa
When you see a locked door, you should just hit it until a crack opens.
eien ni hodokenai nazo nanka wa nai
There's no mystery that lasts forever!
makiokosu, it's a supernova
I made it, it's a supernova!
tobikiri shigekitekina hirameki wo agemashou
Let's flash so bright it'd hurt!
Misskey-Misskey La-Tu-Ma
yume no naka it's a supernova
In my dreams, it's a supernova!
watashi wa sou brain diver
Yeah, I'm the brain diver!
kimi ga sagashi motometeru kotae ni nareru made
Until I can find the answer you're looking for...
Brain diver!
Tower of Parting
（キュービック）カイトが危ない！
Kaito is in danger!
カイトに　生態観察メカを
付けといたんだ。
I installed a bio-observer on him.
It monitors his brain waves, pulse, blood pressure, even his location, and then relays the data.
脳波　脈拍　血圧から居場所まで
カイトの生体データが送られてくる。
（ノノハ）この数値が全部
カイトの危機を示してるって…。
These numbers show that Kaito's in danger?
（アナ）日食…。
えっ？！
Solar eclipse...
アナが思うに　月が
太陽を飲み込もうとしている。
I think... the moon is trying to eat the sun.
もし　あの子が…　ルークって子が
月だとしたら…。
If that boy— Rook is the moon...
（バロン）そのとおりです。
Exactly.
カイト君は今　生命の危機にあると
いってよいでしょう。
It is correct to state that Kaito's life is currently in danger.
His life is?! What do you mean?!
えっ？！　生命の危機って
一体　何が？！
僕　カイトの所へ行く！
I'm going to where Kaito is!
そ　そうだね！　みんなで行こう！
Y-Yeah... Let's all go together!
そうですか。　では　手続きは　私が。
（ギャモン）キレーなんだよな。
I see.
Then let me handle the procedur—
Lovely, isn't it?
訳も分からず　タヌキやキツネに
利用されるのは。
The fox and the raccoon use us without telling us anything.
そろそろ　洗いざらい　ぶちまけて
もらおうか。　学園長さんよ。
It's about time you enlighten us on the details, Principal.
カイト…。
Kaito...
Now... We have plenty of time.
さあて　時間は　たっぷりあるんだ。
ゆっくり聞かせてもらうぜ。
Start talking.
（ソウジ）ああ　そうだね。
You're right.
やっぱ　リフトの数字は
到着する階を示してるんだ。
The number on the lift shows the level it leads to.
Shit...
くそっ！　ううっ！
（回転ノコギリの音）
ふぅ…　しまった！　これじゃ
ルークから離れていっちまう。
Damn, this takes me away from Rook!
（回転ノコギリの音）
ここもかよ！
Here too?!
一体　どうなってんだ。
心の声
パズルを作ったやつの思いが見えね！
What's going on here? I can't hear the feelings of the one who built this puzzle!
いや　思いが　ねえ！
心の声
No, there aren't any feelings!
あるのは　敵意と殺意。
心の声
There's only hostility and murderous intent.
くわっ！
えっ　えい！　えっ　うっ。
ルーク。
Rook!
ルーク！　大丈夫か？　おい　ルーク！
Rook, are you all right? Rook!
しっかりしろ！　ルーク！　ルーク！
Rook, get a hold of yourself!
Rook!
（ルーク）うっ　はっ。
ルーク！　大丈夫か？
Rook! Are you all right?
誰にやられたんだ？！
うっ。
Who caught you?
僕は平気。
I'm all right.
おやじと　おふくろが
守ってくれたのかな…。
My parents protected me, I guess.
こいつのおかげで
薄皮１枚　助かったぜ。
Thanks to this, I got away with just a scratch.
ん？！　あれは？！
That's...
この階だけは　安全みたいだ。
Looks like this level is safe.
ノコギリが　それて
発射口を塞いでる。
The saws block the hole like that.
一体　このパズルは…。
「愚者のパズル」。
What the hell is this puzzle?
A Fools' Puzzle.
The guy who attacked me said that its purpose is to develop the Phi Brain.
「ファイ・ブレインを誕生させる目的で
作られたパズルだ」って→
僕を襲った男が言ってた。
ファイ・ブレイン？
Phi Brain?
ああ…　そのファイ・ブレインの成長を
促すために→
Right. To advance that Phi Brain, there are dangerous traps all over the place.
ここには　過酷な罠が
仕掛けられている。
Those who are led astray by the traps and can't solve the puzzle
その罠に惑わされ　パズルを
解くことができなかった者は→
命を失うと…。
will lose their lives.
そんな？！　そんな忌まわしい
パズルの中に　カイトが？！
And Kaito's in a horrible puzzle like that?
愚者のパズルに　財はない。　パズルを解き
生きて帰ることだけが唯一の目的。
A Fools' Puzzle has no treasure. The only goal is to solve it and get out alive.
むちゃくちゃだよ　そんなのは。
That's crazy.
…で　その「愚者のパズル」が
生みだそうとしている→
And what's this Phi Brain that this Fools' Puzzle is trying to develop?
ファイ・ブレインってのは　何だ？
黄金比にかなった
神の頭脳を持つ者。
Those who have a divine brain of the golden ratio;
神のパズルに挑戦できる
唯一の存在。
the only ones who can challenge the Divine Puzzle.
神のパズル？　何ですか？　それ。
The Divine Puzzle? What's that?
The puzzle into which the ancient sage Pythagoras sealed Divine Revelations.
古代の賢人　ピタゴラスが
神の書を封印したパズルだよ。
ピタゴラスって　ピタピタ？
Pythagoras? You mean Pytha-Pytha?
神のパズルに　神の書か？
うさんくせえな。
Divine Revelations in the Divine Puzzle? Sounds fishy.
神の書に　何が書かれているのか
それを知るのは　ピタゴラス本人だけ。
Only Pythagoras himself knows the contents of the Revelations.
神の書を得た者は　宇宙のあらゆる
謎の答えを知ることができると→
It is said that those who lay hands on the Revelations
will learn the answers to all the mysteries of the universe.
言われている。
They can change the world to their liking and can even evade death.
世界を自由に操ることも　死を
克服することすら可能になると。
それって　もろ
神様ってことなんじゃ…。
That sounds like God.
アナが思うに　それは　人間が
持っては　いけないものかも。
I think... humans shouldn't have that kind of power.
だから　ピタゴラスは
封印したんだろうね。
That's probably why Pythagoras sealed it.
「でも　神に近づきたい」。
「自らが神になりたい」。
"But I want to get closer to God."
"I want to become God myself."
そう願う人々は　太古より
ファイ・ブレインの育成と誕生を→
Since ancient times there have been people who think like that,
and they have worked toward the birth and development of the Phi Brain.
目指してきたんだ。
カイトが　そのファイ・ブレインだってのか？！
あっ！
And Kaito is that Phi Brain guy?
The Principal believes so.
学園長は　こう思っている。
He believes that the four of you, Kaito, Gamon, Cubic and Ana can achieve the Phi Brain...
カイト君　ギャモン君　キュービック君
アナ君の４人は→
ファイ・ブレインの可能性を持つ者…
ファイ・ブレインの子供たちだと。
That you're the children of the Phi Brain.
おおっ！
アナも？
Me too?
僕も？
私だけ違うの？！
And me?
Only I'm not?
ハハハッ。　僕も違うよ。
Neither am I.
ただ　現時点では　オルペウスの腕輪と
契約したカイト君が　最も…。
But at the moment, Kaito, who has contracted the Armband of Orpheus, is the closest...
はぁ？
俺が　そのファイ・ブレインだってのか？
You're saying I'm a Phi Brain as well?
はっ　冗談。　んなわけ　ねえだろう。
Yeah, right! Not a chance.
そうかな？
You think so?
これで　よしっ…　と。
I'm done.
Thanks, Rook.
サンキュー　ルーク。
さっき　うろついたおかげで
だいぶ　ルートは読めたぜ。
I walked around quite a bit, so I more or less know the routes now.
なあ　覚えてるか？
Hey... do you remember?
あの時の約束…。
The promise we made.
組木パズルの…。
ああ　あれか。
About that wooden puzzle.
Ah, that.
もちろんさ。　覚えてるよ。
Of course I remember.
お前と再会できて　あとは…。
We've reunited, now only if...
あの人が居れば…。
...he was here too...
カイト…。
Kaito...
I know finding him is totally hopeless though.
けど　そんなこと言ったって
捜しようねえよな。
あの人は　旅から旅への
風来坊だから。
He went on trip after trip...
真方　ジン。
えっ？！
Makata Jin.
彼の名前は　真方　ジン。
はぁ？！
His name is Makata Jin.
僕は　ジンが今　どこで
どうしているか　知っている。
I know where he is and what he's doing.
まっ　マジかよ？！
S-Seriously?!
本当に　あの人が　どこにいるか
知ってんのかよ！
Do you really know where he is?!
ああ。
どこで会ったんだ？！
あの人は元気なのか？！
Yeah.
Where did you meet him? Is he all right?
心配ない。　元気にしてるよ。
Don't worry, he's all right.
だから　カイト　早く　ここから出よう。
So let's get out of here quick, Kaito.
この愚者のパズルを解くんだ。
Let's solve this Fools' Puzzle.
よし　お前は　ここで待ってろ。
解けたら迎えにくる。
Okay, you wait here then. I'll come back for you after I solve it.
昔から　ルークは　作る専門
俺は　解く専門だったからなぁ。
It's always been you making the puzzles and me solving them.
それから　これ　ノノハスイーツ。
腹減ったら　食えよ。
Also, have some Nonoha sweets if you're hungry.
俺は　ごめんだけどな。
I can't stand them.
ここからは　８階に
上がるしかねえのか。
So I can only go to the 8th from here?
See ya.
心の声
（ルーク）そう。
昔から　カイトは　ソルヴァー。
Exactly. You've always been a Solver...
僕は　ギヴァー。
心の声
And I, a Giver.
だから　ジンは　僕よりも
カイトを。　同じソルヴァーだから。
That's why Jin favored Kaito... as a fellow Solver.
心の声
さあ　本当のパズルタイムは　これからだ。
The real puzzle time starts now.
心の声
３人で過ごしたあの夏は
掛けがえのない俺の宝。
That summer the three of us spent together is a priceless memory to me.
回想
おいしそう！　生クリームみたいだ。
It looks yummy, just like whipped cream!
回想
（ルーク）ウフフフッ。
ねえ　カイト　組木パズル見せて？
回想
えっ？！
Hey Kaito, show me that wooden puzzle!
これの事？
回想
This one?
That puzzle is a memory of your parents, right?
回想
それ　お父さんとお母さんがくれた
思い出のパズルなんだよね。
うん。
回想
僕ね　今
新しい組木パズル作ってるんだ。
You know, I'm making a new wooden puzzle now.
完成したら　カイトにあげる。
回想
えっ？！　ホント？！
I'll give it to you once it's done.
Really?
回想
（ルーク）そしたら　その
組木パズルと一緒に　いつも持ってて。
And then you can have it with you all the time, just like that one.
パズル見るたびに
回想
僕のこと思い出してよ。
And remember me whenever you look at it.
うん！　ありがとう　ルーク！
回想
Okay! Thanks, Rook!
いつまでも一緒！
約束だよ！
うん！
We'll be together forever! It's a promise!
Yeah!
（ジン）今日も　ルークは来ないか…。
Rook's not coming today either?
ん？
転校したんだって。
I heard he changed schools.
ルークに会いたくて　特別教室へ
聞きに行ったんだ。
I went to that special class to ask about him.
When I did...
そしたら…　ルークは転校したって。
They said he transferred to another school...
カイト　人生はパズルだ。
えっ？！
Kaito. Life is a puzzle.
つらく　悲しく　難しいが　それを
解く喜びは　果てしなく大きい。
It's difficult and sad, but it's the greatest joy to solve it.
だから　人は生き続けられる。
That's why people live on.
俺もまた　旅に出ようと思う。
えっ？！
I'm thinking of travelling again.
そんな！　僕　また独りぼっちに
なっちゃうよ！
But... then I'll be all alone again!
パズルが会わせてくれる。
いつか　必ず…。
Puzzles will bring us together again. One day...
それが　お前の運命であり…　使命。
That's your fate... Your destiny.
はっ。
カイト　解いてやれ…　パズルを。
Kaito... Solve puzzles.
（ドアが開く音）
次は　どっちだ？！
Which way next?
もしかしたら
このルートからじゃねえのか。
It might not be from this route.
なにっ？！
What?
This is what it was depicting?!
あれは　このことだったのか！
ルーク！
Rook!
ルーク！　今　助けに行く！
Rook, I'm coming for you!
≫（ルーク）来るな！
あっ。
Don't come!
You won't make it if you come back!
≫戻ったら　間に合わない！
ルーク…。
Rook...
パズルを解くんだ！　大門カイト！
はぁ！
Solve the puzzle, Daimon Kaito!
Hurry!
≫急げ！
心の声
ルークは　殺させねえ。
俺たちは生き延びる！
I won't let you kill Rook. We'll live on!
生きて　生きて２人で
ジンと会うんだ。
We'll live... live and meet Jin again!
フフツ。
今　俺の居るこのルートに
解答はない。
There's no answer on the route I'm following.
見えた。
I can see it now.
（ドアを外す音）
えいっ！
さすが　カイト。
心の声
As expected from Kaito...
He made a shortcut like that.
あんな方法で
心の声
ショートカットルートを作り出すとはね。
出口は　どこだ？
Where is the exit?
本当に　パズルを解いているときの
君は　すてきだよ。
You're truly wonderful when solving puzzles.
But you made a huge mistake.
でも　大変なミスを
犯してしまったね。
パズルを解いても　出口は開かない。
The exit won't open even though you solved the puzzle.
寄り道をして
時間を使い過ぎたからね。
You wasted too much time on false routes.
お前…　どうやって　ここへ？
How did you get here?
このパズルのことは　よく知っている。
I know this puzzle well.
だから　君を招待したんだ。
That's why I invited you here.
今回だけじゃない。
今までの「賢者のパズル」も。
Not only now. Every other Sage Puzzle until now as well.
You overcame your training, grew, and the project advanced to the next stage.
君は試練を乗り越えて　成長し
プロジェクトは　ネクストステージに入った。
オルペウスの腕輪が　君を解放し
本当の姿を見せてくれる。
The Armband of Orpheus frees you and shows us your true self.
それが　未来の君
ファイ・ブレイン　大門カイト。
That's the future you. Phi Brain Daimon Kaito.
オルペウスの腕輪に選ばれた君は
真のファイ・ブレインの子供。
You, chosen by the Armband of Orpheus, are the true child of the Phi Brain.
カイトは　もっと強く
美しくなれるんだよ。
You can become stronger and more beautiful.
何を言ってる。　ルーク！
What are you talking about, Rook?!
エヘヘヘッ。　でも　君には
決定的に足りないものがある。
But there's something you utterly lack.
フフフフッ。
それは　すべてを捨てる覚悟さ。
The determination to throw everything away.
君は　僕を
見捨てるべきだったんだよ！
You should've abandoned me!
何を…　何を言ってる？！　ルーク！
What... What are you saying?!
フッ　まだ分からないのか？
You still don't get it?
僕は　ギヴァー　ＰＯＧのギヴァー。
I'm a Giver. A Giver of the POG.
ルーク君が　ＰＯＧ？！
Rook is in the POG?!
I can't believe that!
信じられない　そんなの！
Rook Banjo Crossfield.
ルーク・盤城・クロスフィールド。
ＰＯＧの総帥　ピタゴラス伯爵の腹心。
Chief of the POG and confidant of Count Pythagoras.
実質的なＰＯＧの　ナンバー２だ。
The true second-in-command of the POG.
あい～！
やっぱり　あの子は　赤い月…。
That boy really is the red moon.
On the orders of Count Pythagoras, he's trying to turn Kaito into a Phi Brain.
彼はピタゴラス伯爵の命を受け　カイト君を
ファイ・ブレインにしようとしている。
神の書を伯爵のものとするために。
To get the Revelations for the Count.
It can't be!
ウソだ。
ウソだ！　ウソだ！　ウソだ！
No! No! No!
フフフッ　信じられない？
いや　信じたくない…　かな？
You can't believe it? Or do you just not want to?
大門カイト　君に命じる。
Daimon Kaito, I order you.
ファイ・ブレインとなり　神のパズルを解け。
僕のために…。
Achieve the Phi Brain and solve the Divine Puzzle. For me...
What... What the hell happened to you?!
一体…
一体　どうしちまったんだよ！
For that, you must first solve the even more dangerous Fools' Puzzle.
そのために　さらに危険な
「愚者のパズル」を解いてもらう。
ははっ。
拒否はできない。
You can't refuse.
ジンは　今　ＰＯＧの手の内に
（ヒビが入る音）
あるのだから。
Jin is in the POG's hands.
心配ない。　僕の命令に従って
ステージをクリアすれば→
Do not worry. If you clear this stage as I command,
すべてを捨てて
ファイ・ブレインとなることができる。
you can throw away everything and achieve the Phi Brain.
そうすれば　ジンにも会えるよ。
カイト。
And then you can meet Jin again, Kaito.
お前…。
You...
心の声
この程度のパズルで
死ぬようなカイトは→
My Kaito would never die from a puzzle of this grade.
心の声
僕のカイトじゃない。
今回は　助けてあげる。
心の声
でも…　２度目はないよ。
I saved you this time. But...
There won't be a second chance.
カイト！
てぇ！
Kaito!
回想
おいしそう！　生クリームみたいだ。
It looks yummy! Just like whipped cream!
回想
（ルーク）ウフフフッ。
いつまでも一緒！
回想
約束だよ！
うん！
We'll be together forever! It's a promise!
カイト！
Kaito!
tsukue no ue de umareta sekai
This world born on my table.
ichiban saki ni kimi ni misetakatta
I wanted you to see it first.
karappo no heya sotto nukedashite hashiri hajimeteta
I sneaked out of the empty room and started to run.
iki hazamasete oka wo noboru to
As I got to the top of the hill, out of breath,
kimi ga saki ni tsuite matteita ne
you were already there waiting for me.
takusan no hajimete kimi to mitsuketa takaramono datta
It was the first of many treasures we would find together.
kanashisa de afureta toki wa
When sorrow was overflowing in me,
nanimo iwazu ni tada soba ni ite kureta ne
you just silently stayed by my side.
ima de mo wasurenai yo
I still haven't forgotten that.
mata aou ne yakusoku wo shiyou
Let's promise we'll meet again.
kie wa shinai ano hi no sayonara
The goodbye of that day we'll never forget.
boku no subete kimi ga kureta michi
All I have I got from you,
zutto kokoro no naka hikaru yo
and it will all shine in my heart forever.